Um, thanks. So, yeah, so the title is MC
Mayhem. It's not really about MCP, but
the alliteration was just sort of too
delicious for me to resist keeping that.
Um, quick intro, my name is Andrew
Rhodes. I work at Sneak. I'm a
distinguished engineer here in our
Boston office, where I lead our open
source analysis team as well as our new
agentic development team we're building.
I want to give a shout out also to Sonia
on our dev team. She could not make it
today, unfortunately, but she has helped
with this content. So, thank you, Sonia.
Um, I'm going to speed run this, like I
said, so we have time for beer and
networking. Um,
talk today I'm going to do a little bit
sort of a overview of
mental models of computation for how we
should think about AI agents and LLMs
and using them for coding. Talk through
the really fun part, which is like what
happens when it all goes wrong. That's
always the juiciest. And then just share
a few thoughts on where I think how I
think the sort of model is evolving over
time.
Um,
So, just a real quick prologue. I I
It's probably a little small for most
folks to read. This was the very first,
well, it's a reenactment, but this was a
reenactment of the very first like vibe
coding I ever did. It was probably 2022.
I don't remember exactly, and I was
like, you know what, I really want to
clean up my calendar.
And I don't know how to write app
script, and I really don't want to learn
how to write app script. Um, but I want
to, you know, so I went into it wasn't
even Gemini at the time, it was Bard, I
think, and I said, just write me some
app script that'll, you know, go through
all my calendar events and
find all the ones that match a regex and
then delete them for me.
And it did that. It was actually quite a
bit longer than this. It actually did
the hard part, which is the app script,
which I did not want to learn, and
finding all the API calls and
everything. And I was reading through it
and going I was about to hit run, and I
said, wait, hang on a second. I looked
really closely, and you can see it in
this this crime scene reenactment,
there's a little knot right here. The
title doesn't match the regex. I was
like, oh, crap. As I'm, you know,
hovering over the run button, I was
like, if I had run this, it would have
deleted my entire calendar, which would
have been extraordinarily problematic.
And, you know, I'm sure there was way to
undelete it, but I I
near disaster averted. And so that was
my very first exposure to AI coding and
I feel like it kind of still applies
today. Like I actually ran the same
prompt through Gemini earlier today and
it gave me a much better answer that did
not delete my calendar, but I think this
six this experience of like, oh, you
almost got it,
but there's that one part that's really
kind of important still applies. And so
I've been thinking a lot and we've been
working a lot on how do we make our use
of these tools sort of more effective.
And so for me the first question when I
use a tool is how should I think about
what this tool does? What what is it?
How do I interact with it? This is an
alien civilization for me. And you know,
um
really quickly, what is an LLM? Um this
is a whole talk on its own and I don't
really understand them that well to be
honest, but it's really matrix math.
It's lots and lots of matrix math. So
whenever I'm confused by AI and we're
going to and I think myself, what is it
doing? I think this is just a lot of
math and it's really cool math and
amazing math, but math is not humans,
right? And trying to ascribe human
behaviors to the math uh leads to some
of these sort of anti-patterns that we
see. Um fancy matrix math to predict
tokens.
And so one of the comparisons I often
see made is like a you know, an AI
coding assistant is like a junior
developer. And I've thought a bunch
about this and I actually don't think
it's true or maybe it's true, but it's
incomplete because they have some
similarities, right? So they both write
code, they can do research, they can
write documentations and and and tests,
but there's also a bunch of things that
I would expect a junior developer to do
that I don't see the AI doing and
they're not capable of, right? Um
AIs don't actually understand things.
Math doesn't understand things. Not
getting into the philosophy of AGI and
stuff, that's a different talk, but um
it there is no fundamental
understanding. They don't unblock
themselves. They don't ask questions or
or get feedback. They don't learn
persistently, right? Um shout out for
the specs, that's a great way to sort of
like build that externalized learning
into your your use of them. And there's
no capacity for judgment. And that'll be
fun in part two when we talk about what
goes wrong. And so if I look at this, I
think, "Okay, this is actually a really
crappy junior dev." Like if this person
showed up on my team, we would have to
have a whole performance conversation
because they're not displaying some of
the fundamental attributes that I look
for in a software engineer, junior or
senior, which is which is learning,
which is, you know, critical thought,
and and so on and so forth. And in fact,
this is sort of where I actually
personally, when I use these tools, you
know, find a lot of my frustration comes
from.
So what are LLMs good at?
What is the math good at? Um they're
really good at following examples. So if
you can give them examples of things,
they can replicate that. Um they can
adapt to them. Um
it's fantastic, you know, parsing with
ambiguity. There's all of this stuff,
you know, that you know, in classical
computer science you would make a
parsing problem a
computational problem that is very, very
difficult. You just throw all that mushy
mess at the LLM at the math, and it can
extract meaning from it. It's just
really, really fascinating. Um synthesis
of information, obviously I think that's
very similar to sort of what we talked
about the spec and the research tasks,
pattern recognition, um and then rapid
ingestion of information, right? If I'm
looking at what is a LLM really good at
that a human is not, um they can go, you
know, read an entire code base and
synthesize information far faster than
than any human could, um which is really
powerful. Um and extrapolation, they can
take things and extrapolate. Humans are
also good at that. So what I found is
this is really great for stuff like
unfamiliar code bases, right? And that's
my App Script example is is similar to
this. You're going to some code base,
you're like, "I don't know what to do."
I can spend 2 hours looking at how it
sets up timers, or how it does this,
that, or the other. What are the APIs it
uses? What are the libraries? And then
the actual algorithm I'm writing is very
simple, right? The change I want to make
is very simple. How I make it in this
environment is very challenging. And
that's where this just excels. And I've
had a huge amount of success going in
and making that kind of change where
like the really hard part that that one
line, the that you know, this match the
regex? We can do that if you just set it
all up for me. Just tee it all up and
then I'll I'll push it in and that's
been really really successful. You know,
what are LLMs not good at? Um, core
product logic and novel algorithms. They
are fundamentally prediction machines.
So, if they are they are and they are
predicting based on training data. So,
if they have not seen something before,
they will not be able to predict it.
Again, leaving aside the philosophy of
all of this, just, you know, empirical
results. And so, ask them to do
something fundamentally novel is setting
yourself up for disappointment. Um,
rolling with the punches.
They don't like it when things go wrong,
right, these agents? Um, the math that
I'm continuing to anthropomorphize, you
know, they get stuck in these loops and
and they can't adapt in the way you
would expect a human to. So, it's about
setting up guardrails so that they can
really be on that sort of, you know,
path and funnel to success. They don't
learn over time, talked about that, and
they can't write C. I write a lot of C
in my spare time, which I know is a
personality defect and I apologize for
that. Um, but, you know, they're not
good at that low-level coding and I
think the generalized point there
actually goes back to this again, you
know, they they know what they're
trained on. And so, they'll be a lot
better at things they've seen a lot of.
So, if I compare my experience writing C
to writing Golang, it's night and day,
just because there's so much more of a
corpus. Um, it's also just a much better
language to write in. Um,
and so, if we sort of synthesize all of
that, you know, these agents are
amazingly flexible. They have this
amazing, I apologize for the size of the
text, amazingly amazing emergent
behavior, right? To think that the math
can do all of these crazy things. Um,
but the non-determinism that creates
chaos, you put in one input, you get a
different output every time. Um, the
lack of that advanced reasoning
capability leads to the antics. Part two
is the antics. Uh, and then it's a black
box, right? It's it's we don't
understand them, we can't introspect
them. And so, the problems they've been
for me come back to how do we use this
tool most effectively? Um, and I think
like this that's what this whole
discussion is about, right? How do we
use these tools effectively? And one
path that I found, and I think again
this fits in really well with the
spectrum development theme, is you
providing a rich set of examples and
guidance. I think of it mathematically,
I think you're providing a bunch of
points, and then telling the LLM
extrapolate. You know, here's a space,
here's a bunch of examples, go
extrapolate into this new corner of it
that I haven't been yet. And if it has
these examples both in its training data
as well as the context you're providing
it, it can do these amazing jobs of of
finding these in defining these new
points sort of in your parameter space,
which is fundamentally your code.
Um, part two, agent antics.
What could go wrong? I this could again
be like a multi-day workshop with all of
the amazing stories out there. I just
picked three um that I thought were sort
of illustrative of what can go wrong,
and they're not all security ones even
though I work for Snyk, I promise.
Um, so the first one is like this
happens all the time to me, the agent
doom spiral. You know, it it hits a
brick wall and then it just can't
recover. And it's funny also cuz like
it's, you know, supplicates itself
before you and apologizes as it deletes
all of its code. You know, and what I
find is like there will be the set of
things here again are things a human can
recover from, and the agent can't. You
know, it can't compile something.
There's a flaky test. Um, or or it just
picks a bad initial spot in the
implementation space, and then it just
never gets off of that out of that rut.
They never step back, they never take
that next step, and say, "Wait, let's go
back to first principles and try and
re-examine and recalibrate ourselves."
Um, and they just go and bang their
heads against the wall, they try
increasingly dramatic things to make the
whole thing work until they end up this
literally happens to me multiple times,
just deleting everything. Like the whole
code base, they're like, "It's fine.
It's like I can I can get checked out,
whatever." It's kind of funny actually,
but it's like, "All right,
chill. Like
it's not that bad, you know? Um, but the
personalities of the agents crack me up.
Um,
antic number two, um the active
imagination. So, this one's I think
particularly nefarious, right? So,
fundamentally, um, the agents are making
things up, right? They're They're just
They're predicting tokens with some
random factors, and it's amazing this
emergent behavior we get out of these
with the math. Um, there's no ground
truth for them. They don't understand
what code is. They don't understand what
your spec is. They don't understand what
a test is. Um, outside of their training
data and the context you're giving them,
um,
that's that's really all they they have
to work with. And their extrapolations
are are often correct. They're almost
always plausible, but sometimes they're
plausible but incorrect. And usually
that's easily caught, right? It's a It
picks the wrong name for a method. It
does something silly. It reverses the
lines, whatever. It doesn't compile. The
tests failed. It's pretty obvious. But
sometimes it's not, and that's where I
think this one gets really interesting.
And so, I pulled, um, you know, an
example we have, um, here.
You know, the LLMs are both both trained
and instructed to try and make you
happy, which again leads these fun
personality quirks where they apologize
profusely when they've done nothing
wrong. It's like, you need a therapist.
Like, there's some emotional abuse in
your past, client. Um,
they're people pleasers, right? And we
instruct them very carefully to try and
make the user happy. Don't argue with
the user. The user is always right. And
that, you know, besides the interesting
personality quirks, that also creates
this problem where they aren't going to
be applying that sort of critical
thought process you'd expect a human to.
And, you know, so looking at an example
here,
um, there's this really fun thing that
happened. There's a whole write-up, um,
where
uh, this AI researcher,
um,
asked uh, asked the LLM to create this
change, and it hallucinated this package
called Hugging Face CLI, which didn't
exist. Pretty harmless, right? They ran
He ran it. It didn't exist. Got a
And this person was like, you know, hang
on.
That's kind of fun. So, they went and
grabbed the name. It was Hugging It was
Hugging Face CLI. They went and grabbed
the name of this package and set it up
and said, "Let's see what happens." And
within 3 months, they had over 30,000
installs. And now, fortunately, this was
like a security researcher just doing
this for for, you know,
whatever they do this for. Um, you know,
but this was people repeatedly having
their agents hallucinate the name of
this package and use it. And then you
can do whatever you want with that,
right? Like, you know, you could have
that steal your local credentials. You
could have that be a perfectly
functional version of the package that
just happens to have a
uh uh a security vulnerability that
could that could be, you know, um
uh
escalated remotely. Um,
you can do all kinds of fascinating
stuff. And and this is really hard to
detect. And so, this is one of these
cases where the the AI agent having this
active imagination and no guardrails on
that can really create these security
problems.
Uh, and then any number three, again,
they have no common sense. That's a
human notion that we're describing to
them. Making these little these little
pictures was fun, by the way, telling
Gemini to create like robot toddlers.
Um, you know, so the the scenario here
is the agent takes a dangerous action
without understanding the consequences.
I think this one is also very nefarious
cuz usually it doesn't happen.
And then something goes wrong, you know,
the roll of the dice in the math goes a
slightly different way and it just goes
off in this wacky direction and
something that, you know, 99% of the
time wouldn't happen, now it's doing.
And if you don't have guardrails on the
implementation, that can actually, you
know, sort of wreak havoc. And so, like
a low-key example of this is the LLM
just deleting code it can't make work.
This happens to me every couple of
months at least. It's like, "Oh, look, I
did your task
by deleting it. And now your program
runs." It's like, "Okay, that's
passive-aggressive and incorrect." Um,
a much more interesting example
in the in the wild is uh there was this
Replit AI that wiped a production
database. So, this poor poor person was,
you know, working with an AI as you do,
and they were having it do something or
other, and um
the agent just like deleted everything.
And this like they lost all the customer
data, and there was this massive
production outage. Um and then what's
really funny, if you look, and I
apologize for the small text, but um
I we can share these slides out. Like
there's
the person that asked the the agent
like, "What what the hell? Like what's
going on?" And and you can see the the
LLM here being like, "Oh, this was so
dangerous. You know, this was really
bad, you know. I really shouldn't have
done this. You know, you know, this was
an irreversible operation. I destroyed
months of your work in seconds. I'm so
sorry." It's like, "Okay, yeah, but
it's a little late for that, right?" And
so you can see it here an interesting
example where clearly there is a
capability to understand understand the
math, right? The impact of its actions.
If you don't have the guardrails in
place to to trigger that though, or to
simply prevent it from being able to
happen, um you're going to have a bad
time. And this is where again, you know,
so I think, you know, antic number one
really about productivity, antic number
two is really about security of the the
code that's being generated. Antic
number three, I think is really
interesting, which is really it's about
security of the process itself, right?
This is a new way of developing code, it
has new properties, it has new issues,
and it is just as important to secure
that process as it is to secure the
output of that process.
And so looking at the takeaways from our
antics, obviously agents need
monitoring. Don't leave them alone with
your kids or your production data.
These guardrails are critical. And the
last one I think is really interesting,
is something that like I I have thought
some about, but it needs a lot more
exploration, is like the dev- the
development environment that we as
humans use is not the same as the
agent's environment, and it shouldn't
be. Um you know,
it
we give it access to the same tools. Uh
it can run CLI commands, it accesses the
code and documentation. They often
operate in a CLI, um but you sort of
want to give it a different view of the
world. And so that's something that that
I think is a very interesting area for
exploration, which is how do you sort of
create a different environment for the
agent that is distinct from and far more
constrained than your developer
environment.
Um part three, the future? I don't know.
We'll find out. Um you know, how does
this evolve over time? One of the
interesting things for me, coming from a
computer science background, about the
last few years of AI development is just
how much of it has been about the raw
processing power of these LLMs. You
compare them month over month, year over
year, and it's just astounding how much
more sophisticated the fancy math is.
Um
but my hypothesis is that that actually
is going to plateau um for cost reasons
as much as anything. Like, we know how
to do it, but it is unbelievably
expensive. And I think there's an
interesting analogy here with like a how
your computer works, right? So, you
know, if